Guide to the Carroll T. Hobart Papers
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Carroll T. Hobart papers
1871-1904
WA MSS S-2396
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
7.31
(11 boxes) + 2 broadside folders
The papers document Carroll T. Hobart's involvement in the Yellowstone Park Improvement Company and the Northern Pacific Railroad through correspondence, photographs, printed material, and documents. The correspondence consists mostly of Hobart's business correspondence. Principal correspondents include his wife Alice, his contractor brother Charles F. Hobart, and T. F. Oakes and Robert Harris of the Northern Pacific Railroad. The photographs include images of Yellowstone National Park by F. Jay Haynes, William Henry Jackson, and Carleton Watkins, in stereographs, cabinet cards and unmounted albumen prints. The papers also include documents and financial papers relating to the Yellowstone Park Improvement Company and the Northern Pacific Railroad, two pen-and-ink maps, one of them a plat map of Cinnabar, Montana, and two office journals from 1881-1882.
Hobart, Carroll T.
Haynes, F. Jay (Frank Jay), 1853-1921
Jackson, William Henry, 1843-1942
Watkins, Carleton E., 1829-1916
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Purchased from William Reese Company on the Frederick W. & Carrie S. Beinecke Fund for Western Americana, 1987.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Box 11: Restricted fragile material. Reference surrogates have been substituted in the main files. For further information consult the appropriate curator.
CARROLL T. HOBART
Carroll T. Hobart was a Northern Pacific Railroad Superintendent and manager of the Yellowstone Park Improvement Company early in the history of commercial enterprises in Yellowstone Park. Hobart had served as a railroad superintendent for at least ten years when he was made Superintendent of the Yellowstone Park Branch of the Northern Pacific Railroad in 1881. Shortly after this he formed an improvement company with two other men, Henry F. Douglas, a merchant of Fort Yates, Dakota Territory, and Rufus Hatch, a New York banker.
The company sought from the federal government a monopoly to construct roadways and build hotels in Yellowstone Park, but no monopoly was granted, and in 1883 a modified agreement was reached with the Secretary of the Interior. Rufus Hatch, the principal financial backer, never supplied the necessary capital, and Hobart, acting as general manager of the company, built the National Hotel at Mammoth Hot Springs largely on credit. Yellowstone Park Superintendents charged him with exploiting park resources: contracting with local hunters for wild meat to feed his workmen and later hotel guests, as well as cutting timber for his sawmill without authorization. The hotel lost money its first summer of operation (1883), and during the winter of 1883-1884 carpenters staged a strike for their wages. When creditors began demanding money, Rufus Hatch, in New Jersey, sought the appointment of a receiver without his partners' knowledge. In turn, Hobart and Douglas obtained a receiver in the Wyoming courts. This receiver, George B. Hulme, eventually won control of the company's assets.
After the summer of 1884 proved to be another losing season, Hulme leased the hotel to Hobart for $1 in 1885. Hobart thereupon made the hotel a money-making operation which thrived. The Yellowstone Park Improvement Company was later sold to an agent of the Northern Pacific Railroad Company.
Carroll was married to Alice M. Hobart, and they had at least one son. In 1898 he was engaged in the location and construction of a government road in the Argentine Republic.
Scope and Contents
The papers document Carroll T. Hobart's involvement with Yellowstone National Park through correspondence, photographs, printed material and documents. The collection consists of four series: Correspondence, Photographs, Printed Material, and Other Papers, and spans the dates 1871-1904.
Series I, Correspondence, consists primarily of business correspondence, including incoming letters and drafts of outgoing letters. The series has been arranged chronologically. The earliest correspondence is in the form of a letterpress copybook for the years 1871-1872. There are approximately 500 letterpress copies of outgoing letters and reports sent by Hobart while Superintendent of the Minnesota Division of the Northern Pacific Railroad. The letters concern supplies, reports of work on the line, and other construction matters. The remainder of the correspondence, in the form of individual letters, dates from 1881 through 1898. These letters largely concern his work as manager of the Yellowstone National Park Improvement Company. The nearly twenty letters to his wife are full of detail about his work, and thirty-five letters from his brother Charles describe daily events at the hotel, including the carpenter strike in the winter of 1883-1884. Other correspondents include T. F. Oakes and Robert Harris of the Northern Pacific Railroad, and Henry M. Teller, Secretary of the Interior. A letter from Rufus Hatch to Hobart dated July 3, 188[-] contains a letter of introduction to Henry Ward Beecher. There are very few personal letters; three of them are from Carroll's mother in Appleton, Wisconsin, two of which are undated, the other is dated March 1886. Typescript transcripts of the correspondence are in four folders at the end of the series; these transcripts were made by an unidentified person, and have not been checked against the correspondence. They are accompanied by photocopies of documents, financial papers, and printed material, arranged in chronological order.
Series II, Photographs, is organized by photographer into six subseries: F. Jay Haynes, Keystone View Company, H.C. Phillips, W.H. Jackson & Co., Carleton Watkins, and Unidentified. The views are predominantly of Yellowstone National Park at the time Hobart worked there and also include portraits of Carroll Hobart and his family. The twenty-two Haynes photographs include eight stereocards from the Yellowstone National Park series, several mounted photographs (17.4 x 25 cm.) from different photographic series, and a mounted photograph entitled "Conductors' Excursion to the National Park, June 1885." The forty-two Jackson photographs (some of them duplicates) are mounted and unmounted albumen photographs, including two photographs measuring 16.5 x 27 cm. The forty-six Watkins photographs include mounted albumen photographs from Watkins' New Boudoir Series, and unmounted albumen photographs from Watkins' New Series.
Series III, Printed Material, is organized by format into five subseries: Books, Catalogs, Pamphlets, Periodicals, and Other Printed Material. Within each subseries, the materials are arranged alphabetically by author or title. Series IV, Other Papers, consists of documents, financial papers, maps, and other papers. These include two folders of documents and financial papers relating to the Yellowstone National Park Improvement Company, and the Northern Pacific Railroad Company; a file of bills and receipts for both personal and professional expenses; two pen-and-ink maps, one of Fracl Township in Yellowstone National Park, and the other an 1883 plat of the town of Cinnabar, Montana; and two office journals covering 1881-1882 containing information on his work on the Northern Pacific Railroad in North Dakota.
Oversize consists of materials from Series II, III, and IV, and is arranged in box order.
Cinnabar (Mont.) -- Maps; Yellowstone National Park -- Pictorial works; Yellowstone National Park -- History; Albumen prints; Cabinet photographs; Maps (documents); Photographic prints; Plats; Stereographs; Harris, Robert, 1830-1894; Hobart, Alice; Hobart, Carroll T.; Hobart, Charles F.; Oakes, Thomas F.; Northern Pacific Railroad Company; Yellowstone Park Improvement Company
- Correspondence, 1871-1898; Series I; 1.42; (2 boxes)
  Scope and Contents
  Series I, Correspondence, is arranged chronologically.
  - Letterpress copybook, 1871-72 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence, 1881-82 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence, 1883 (Box 2, Folder 3-5)
  - Correspondence, 1884 (Box 2, Folder 6-12)
  - Correspondence, 1885 (Box 2, Folder 13-15)
  - Correspondence, 1886 (Box 2, Folder 16-17)
  - Correspondence, 1887-88 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Correspondence, 1889-98 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Correspondence (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Typescript transcripts of the correspondence (Box 2, Folder 21-24)
    Accompanied by photocopies of documents, financial papers, and printed material, arranged in chronological order
- Photographs, [1881]-1904; Series II; 1.83; (4 boxes)
  Series II, Photographs, is organized into six subseries: F. Jay Haynes, Keystone View Company, H.C. Phillips, W.H. Jackson & Co., Carleton Watkins, and Unidentified.
  - HAYNES, F. JAY
    - Yellowstone National Park. 8 mounted stereocards, 10 x 17.8 cm. (Box 3, Folder 25)
      Six photographs numbered: 1031, [1401?], 1460, 1946, 1954, 1977
    - Cabinet Series of Noted Indian Chiefs and Northern Pacific Views illustrating the Yellowstone National Park. Two cabinet card photographs, 10 x 15.8 cm. on mounts 10.8 x 16.4 cm. (Box 3, Folder 26)
    - Conductor's Excursion to the National Park, June 1885. One mounted photograph, 14.9 x 22.6 cm. on mount 17.3 x 24.8 cm. (Box 3, Folder 27)
    - Northern Pacific Views. Yellowstone National Park. Four mounted photographs, 16.1 x 23 cm. on mounts 17.4 x 24.9 cm., n.d. (Box 3, Folder 28)
    - Yellowstone National Park. Three mounted photographs, 23.1 x 16.2 cm. on mounts 25 x 17.4 cm., n.d. (Box 3, Folder 29)
    - Portraits of [Carroll T. Hobart?] and James O. Hobart. Four cabinet card photographs, 14.9 x 9.9 cm. on mounts 16.5 x 19.8 cm. and smaller, [1881 or 82?] (Box 3, Folder 30)
  - KEYSTONE VIEW COMPANY
    - 13581. Rocky Mountain Divide, Yellowstone National Park, Wyo., U.S.A. One mounted stereocard, 8.9 x 17.8 cm., 1904 (Box 3, Folder 31)
      Copyright 1904 by B.L. Singley
  - PHILLIPS, H. C.
    - Family portrait of Carroll T., Alice and James Hobart. One cabinet card photograph, 14.3 x 10.3 cm. on mount 16.5 x 10.8 cm., [1884 or 85?] (Box 3, Folder 32)
  - W.H. JACKSON & CO.
    - Photographs of Rocky Mountain Scenery, Denver, Colorado. 7 mounted photographs, 10.5 x 16.7 cm. on mounts 11.5 x 17.8 cm., n.d. (Box 3, Folder 33)
      Photographs numbered: 4009, 4024, [4029?], 4033, 4034, 4053, 4057
    - Photographs of Rocky Mountain Scenery, Denver, Colorado. 29 unmounted photographs, 16.4 x 10.1 cm., n.d. (Box 4, Folder 34)
      Photographs numbered: 4006 (2), 4008 (2), 4009 (2), 4012 (2), 4017 (2), 4018, 4036, 4041 (2), 4044 (2), 4060, 4052 (2), 4053 (2), 4056, 4060 (2), 4064, 4065. Two images unnumbered, and a duplicate
    - Photographs of Rocky Mountain Scenery, Denver, Colorado. 1 unmounted matted photograph. 16.5 x 27 cm., n.d.
      Photograph numbered 3053
    - Stereocards of Boiling Springs. Two mounted stereocards, 10 x 17.8 cm., n.d. (Box 5, Folder 35)
      Photographs numbered: 3977, 3994
    - Summit Basins, Mammoth Hot Springs. 1 unmounted matted photograph. 16.6 x 26.5 cm., n.d.
    - Yellowstone National Park. Two mounted photographs, 10.4 x 16.6 cm. on mounts 11.4 x 17.8 cm., n.d. (Box 5, Folder 36)
      Photographs numbered 4006, 4066
  - WATKINS, CARLETON
    - Watkins' New Boudoir Series, Yo Semite, Pacific Coast, Yellowstone Park, &c. 15 mounted photographs, 12.1 x 20.9 cm. on mounts 13.8 x 21.5 cm., n.d. (Box 5, Folder 37-38)
      Photographs numbered: D219, D221, D222, D224, D225, D227, D229, D230, D231 (2), D234, D235, D237, D240, D241
    - Watkins New Series. 27 unmounted photographs, 11.9 x 19.5 cm., n.d. (Box 6, Folder 39)
      Photographs numbered: D219-228, D230-235, D237 (2), D239-240 (2), D241-242, D244, D246-248
    - Watkins New Series. 4 unmounted matted photographs. 38 x 53.3 cm., n.d.
      Photographs numbered S101, S103, S108, S114
  - UNIDENTIFIED
    - Group portrait, people unidentified. One mounted photograph, 6.7 x 9.7 cm. on mount 8.9 x 11.4 cm., n.d. (Box 6, Folder 40)
- Printed Material, 1880-1884; Series III; 0.42; (1 box)
  Series III, Printed Material, is organized into five subseries: Books, Catalogs, Pamphlets, Periodicals, and Other Printed Material. Within each subseries, they are arranged alphabetically by author or title.
  - BOOKS
    - Haupt, Herman, Jr. The Yellowstone National Park. New York and Philadelphia: J. M. Stoddart, c1883 (Box 7, Folder 41)
    - Yellowstone National Park. 1882-'84. Bound volume of government documents relating to Yellowstone, [1884] (Box 7, Folder 42)
  - CATALOGS
    - American Iron Works. Jones & Laughlins, Chicago, Manufacturers of American and Clair Bar, Hoop, Sheet and Plate Iron, Bridge Iron... [Chicago], 1881 Feb (Box 7, Folder 43)
    - Ames Manufacturing Co. Price List and Illustrated Catalogue of Wrought Iron Pipe and Fittings for Steam, Gas and Water, Tubing, Casing and Boiler Flues, Brass Goods, Rig Irons, Drilling Tools and Supplies, for Oil or Artesian Wells. Titusville, PA.: Morning Herald Print, 1880 (Box 7, Folder 44)
    - Catalogue of Oshkosh Carriage Co. Successor to Oshkosh & Goodfellow, Buggies and Farmers' Spring Wagons, Oshkosh, Wis. 1883-84. (Box 7, Folder 45)
    - Price List. E. Moneuse, 128 South 5th Avenue, Patentee of the Revolving Grates, and Manufacturer of French Cooking Ranges, Broilers, Hot Water Carving Tables, Coffee, Tea, and Water Urns, Also Copper, Tin and Iron Cooking Utensils for Hotels, Restaurants, Steamers, Public and Religious Institutions and Private Dwellings. New York: Press of Mitchell A. C. Levy, 1882 Jan (Box 7, Folder 46)
    - S.H. & E.Y. Moore, Agents for Providence Tool Company, Reading Bolt and Nut Works...and Other Manufacturers of Heavy Hardware, Railway Supplies, Ship Chandlery Hardware, Etc. and Manufacturers of 'Climax' Barn Door Hangers, Moore's Differential Pulley Blocks, Moore's Freight Car Hangers and Rollers, Etc. [Chicago], 1882 (Box 7, Folder 47)
    - To Mechanics. Facts and Suggestions Regarding the Right Choice and Right Use of Solid Emery Wheels, and Emery Grinding Machinery. From the Tanite Co., Stroudsburg, Monroe Co., Pa. New York: John Polhemus, c1882 (Box 7, Folder 48)
    - The United States Electric Lighting Company. New York: Press of J.W. Pratt, [1883] (Box 7, Folder 49)
  - PAMPHLETS
    - Billings. The Agricultural Stock Raising and Mining Centre of the Yellowstone Valley. The Bonanza Town on the Whole Line of the Northern Pacific Railroad. New York: E. Wells Sackett & Rankin, Steam Book and Job Printers, 1882 (Box 7, Folder 50)
    - For Sale 108,000 Acres of Timber and Iron Lands Including a Delightful Summer Resort on Projected and Near Constructed Rail Roads. (Box 7, Folder 51)
    - H.R. 7595. In the Senate of the United States... An Act Making appropriations for sundry civil expenses of the government for the fiscal year ending June thirtieth, eighteen hundred and eighty-four, and for other purposes. [Washington: Government Printing Office], [1883] (Box 7, Folder 52)
    - H.R. 7380. In the Senate of the United States... An Act Making appropriations for sundry civil expenses of the Government for the fiscal year ending June thirtieth, eighteen hundred and eighty-five, and for other purposes. [Washington: Government Printing Office], [1884] (Box 7, Folder 53)
    - In the Senate of the United States. ... Mr. Sawyer, from the Committee on Railraods, submitted the following Report... Senate Report No. 239. [Washington: Government Printing Office], 1884 (Box 7, Folder 54)
    - Land and Farming in North Dakota on the Northern Pacific Railroad. Manchester: T. Sowler & Co. Printers ... Reprinted by the Pioneer Press Co. St. Paul, Minn. (Box 7, Folder 55)
    - Manual of Telegraphy and Description of Instruments Adapted for Use on Private Telegraph Lines. New York: J.H. Bunnell & Co., 1883 (Box 7, Folder 56)
    - Montana: Its Climate, Soil, Scenery, Resources and Industries. Its Advantages for General Farming, Cattle Raising, Wool Growing, Mining, and Other Occupations. New York: Published at the Office of the "The Northwest", 1883 (Box 7, Folder 57)
    - North Dakota. Its Development and Resources. Being a Statement submitted to the Committee on Territories of the two Houses of Congress in January, 1882. Washington, D.C.: National Republican Printing House (Box 7, Folder 58)
    - Report of the Governor of Wyoming, Made to the Secretary of the Interior. 1883. Washington: Government Printing Office (Box 7, Folder 59)
    - The Yellowstone National Park Improvement Company. Charter, By-Laws, and List of Officers and Directors., 1883 (Box 7, Folder 60)
  - PERIODICALS
    - Congressional Record. Vol. 15, No. 130. Washington, 1884 May 28 (Box 7, Folder 61)
    - The Helena Era. Vol. 1, No. 5. Helena, Montana, 1883 Aug 25
    - Northwestern Presbyterian. Vol I, Nos. 36-40. Minneapolis and St. Paul, 1885 Aug-Sep
      Two copies of No. 40
  - OTHER PRINTED MATERIAL
    - Strum, G. P. Montana Territory. Map "compiled from the official Records of the General Land Office and other sources", 1883
    - Clippings, [1882]-83, n.d. (Box 7, Folder 62)
    - Business cards, n.d. (Box 7, Folder 63)
- Other Papers, 1872-1889; Series IV; 0.42; (1 box)
  Series IV, Other Papers, is organized into four subseries: Documents, Financial Papers, Maps and Drawings, and Other Materials.
  - DOCUMENTS
    - Contracts and deeds for land in Brainerd, Minnesota; Gallatin County, Montana; and Park County, Montana, 1872-89 (Box 8, Folder 64)
    - Yellowstone National Park Improvement Company documents and financial papers, 1882-85, n.d. (Box 8, Folder 65)
    - Petitions to and receipts from Northern Pacific Rail Road Company, 1883-89, n.d. (Box 8, Folder 66)
  - FINANCIAL PAPERS
    - Bills and receipts, 1872-87, n.d. (Box 8, Folder 67)
    - Check register, 1884-86 (Box 8, Folder 68)
  - MAPS AND DRAWINGS
    - "Fracl Township. No. 9 South Range No. 8 East of the Principal Meridian Montana. Yellowstone National Park." Pen-and-ink plat map
    - Jackson, Charles E. Schematic for a pile trestle. Pen-and-ink and wash
    - "Plat of the Town of Cinnabar, Gallatin County, M.T. Terminus of the N.P. Park Branch." Pen-and-ink plat map, 1883
  - OTHER MATERIALS
    - List of unidentified lots, n.d. (Box 8, Folder 69)
    - Office journal, 1881 (Box 8, Folder 70)
    - Office journal, 1882 (Box 8, Folder 71)
    - Itinerary of a European trip, 1887 May 20 (Box 8, Folder 72)
    - Dried flower, n.d. (Box 8, Folder 73)
- Oversize, 3.01; (2 boxes)
  Oversize consists of materials from Series II, III, and IV, and is arranged in box order.
  - Photographs of Rocky Mountain Scenery, Denver, Colorado. 1 unmounted matted photograph. 16.5 x 27 cm. (in Series II) (Box 9, Folder 74)
  - Summit Basins, Mammoth Hot Springs. 1 unmounted matted photograph. 16.6 x 26.5 cm. (in Series II), n.d. (Box 9, Folder 75)
  - Watkins New Series. 4 unmounted matted photographs. 38 x 53.3 cm. (in Series II) (Box 9, Folder 76)
  - The Helena Era. Vol. 1, No. 5. Helena, Montana (in Series III), 1883 Aug 25 (Box 10, Folder 77)
  - Northwestern Presbyterian. Vol I, Nos. 36-40. Minneapolis and St. Paul (in Series III), 1885 Aug-Sep (Box 10, Folder 78-80)
  - Deeds (in Series IV), 1872-89 (Box 10, Folder 81)
  - Yellowstone National Park Improvement Company documents and financial papers (in Series IV), 1882-85, n.d. (Box 10, Folder 82)
  - "Fracl Township. No. 9 South Range No. 8 East of the Principal Meridian Montana. Yellowstone National Park." Pen-and-ink plat map (in Series IV) (Box 10, Folder 83)
  - Jackson, Charles E. Schematic for a pile trestle. Pen-and-ink and wash (in Series IV) (Box 10, Folder 84)
  - Strum, G. P. Montana Territory. Map "compiled from the official Records of the General Land Office and other sources" (in Series III), 1883 (Box bsd, folder 85)
  - "Plat of the Town of Cinnabar, Gallatin County, M.T. Terminus of the N.P. Park Branch." Pen-and-ink plat map (in Series IV), 1883 (Box bsd, folder 86)
- Restricted Fragile Papers, 0.21; (1 box)
  Conditions Governing Access
  Restricted fragile material. Reference surrogates have been substituted in the main files. For further information consult the appropriate curator.
  - Box 2, folders 10 and 12 (Box 11, Folder 87)